<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The vniuersall principle the common iustice of the world, and the royall law of love : deliuered in a sermon at the assises in Dorchester, the 23. day of Iuly, anno Dom. 1629 / by I.M. ...</title>
            <author>Mayo, John K.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1630</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 40 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 13 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-12">2011-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A07372</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 17756</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S1301</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">22106858</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 22106858</idno>
            <idno type="VID">25081</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A07372)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 25081)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 1732:3)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The vniuersall principle the common iustice of the world, and the royall law of love : deliuered in a sermon at the assises in Dorchester, the 23. day of Iuly, anno Dom. 1629 / by I.M. ...</title>
                  <author>Mayo, John K.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[23] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed for Iohn Smithuuike,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1630.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Dedication signed: Iohn Mayo.</note>
                  <note>Signatures: A-C⁴ (last page blank).</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Bible. --  N.T. --  Matthew VII, 12 --  Sermons.</term>
               <term>Golden rule --  Sermons.</term>
               <term>Sermons, English --  17th century.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2010-03</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-03</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-05</date>
            <label>Susie Lorand</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-10</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Rekeyed and resubmitted</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-12</date>
            <label>Kayla Ondracek</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-12</date>
            <label>Kayla Ondracek</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:25081:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>The Vniuerſall Principle;</p>
            <p>THE COMMON IVSTICE OF THE WORLD, AND <hi>THE ROYALL LAW</hi> OF LOVE: Deliuered in a Sermon at the <hi>Aſſiſes</hi> in <hi>Dorcheſter,</hi> the 23. day of <hi>Iuly, Anno Dom.</hi> 1629.</p>
            <p>By <hi>I. M.</hi> Rector of CATISTOCKE.</p>
            <q>
               <p>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nuſquiſque quod ſibi fieri non vult, alteri nequaquam faciat. Qui ſic facit peccatum non nutrit.</p>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>Auguſtinus. Serm. 62. ad fratres in Eremo.</hi>
               </bibl>
            </q>
            <p>LONDON, Printed for IOHN SMITHVVIKE. <hi>An. Dom.</hi> 1630.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:25081:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:25081:2"/>
            <head>TO THE RIGHT WORSHIPFVLL AND Nobly deſcended, HENRY HASTINGS <hi>Eſquire,</hi> one of his MAIESTIES <hi>Iuſtices</hi> of <hi>Peace,</hi> and one of the <hi>Deputie Lieftenants</hi> in the Countie of <hi>Dorſet.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">Y</seg>Our approbation of that <hi>Sermon</hi> which was preached at the <hi>Aſſiſes</hi> laſt in <hi>Dor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cheſter,</hi> with your good countenance, and louing ſpeeches, which it pleaſed you then to vſe vnto mee for the ſame: hath emboldened me, and made me pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſume, to let it come to the view of the world; for which I humbly intreat your fauourable acceptation, and your Patronage and Protection against them that ſhall bee found auerſe or with any ſiniſter affection to taxe or tra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duce the ſame. Thus wiſhing vnto you yours, many good and ioyfull New-yeares, with the beſt welfare and happineſſe, that can be deſired or imagined, I leaue you to the Shepheard and Biſhop of our ſoules; and reſt,</p>
            <closer>
               <dateline>
                  <hi>Catiſtocke,</hi> 
                  <date>Ian. 1.</date>
               </dateline>
               <signed>Your Worſhips to be commanded. <hi>IOHN MAYO.</hi>
               </signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="to_the_reader">
            <pb facs="tcp:25081:3"/>
            <head>To the Reader.</head>
            <p>Courteous and charitable <hi>READER,</hi> I was very loth to make my weakeneſſe knowne vnto others, which is beſt knowne to my ſelfe, but being ouer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>intreated by ſome ſpeciall friends of mine; I was at laſt induced to yeeld vnto their deſire, and to haue this pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſhed. Faine I would, but I cannot pleaſe all. I hope I ſhall pleaſe the beſt, ſuch as make conſcience of their wayes, and doe as the would be done vnto. VVhich, if it were as well followed and practiſed, as it is ſpoken of and commended; we ſhould haue amongſt vs more fruits of the ſpirit, and leſſe workes of the fleſh, more pietie, peace and charitie, and leſſe prophaneneſſe, ſuits, troubles and iniuries, then we haue in theſe dayes. Reade therefore, and cenſure charitably. Pardon I pray thee what is amiſſe by any defects or imperfections, and in the feare of the Lord;</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Fac alijs fieri quod cupis ipſe tibi. Thine in Chriſt Ieſus; IOH. MAYO.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb facs="tcp:25081:3"/>
            <head>THE VNIVERSALL PRINCIPLE.</head>
            <epigraph>
               <q>
                  <bibl>
                     <hi>MAT. 7. VERSE 12.</hi>
                  </bibl>
                  <p>Therefore, whatſoeuer yee would that men ſhould doe to you, euen ſo doe yee to them; for this is the Law and the Prophets.</p>
               </q>
            </epigraph>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>Heſe wordes are the wordes of our Sauiour CHRIST to his Diſciples when hee was vpon the Mount; and there opened his mouth and taught them, the firſt time that euer was in publike.</p>
            <p>Which words containe in them two principall parts; A generall Rule of Iuſtice, ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken out of a Collation of Similies, and a reaſon or te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtimoniall Confirmation of the ſame. A generall rule of Iuſtice out of a Collation of Similies in theſe words; <hi>Therefore whatſoeuer ye would that men ſhould doe to you, euen ſo doe ye to them;</hi> The reaſon or teſtimoniall Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firmation of the ſame in theſe words; <hi>for this is the Law and the Prophets.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb facs="tcp:25081:4" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>
               <hi>Therefore.]</hi> This word concludes and inferres our Sauiour Chriſts intent and purpoſe, and ſhewes the ſcope and the ſumme of that which is precedent in the Chapter; namely, that to doe to others as we would be done vnto our ſelues, is the Law and the Prophets, that is, the ſumme of doctrine ſet downe in the Law and the Prophets.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Whatſoeuer ye would,]</hi> or, all things whatſoeuer yee would, <hi>rationabili &amp; diſcreta voluntate,</hi> ſaith <hi>Dionyſius Carthuſianus</hi> vpon this place; <hi>rationabiliter, vtiliter, &amp; fideliter,</hi> ſaith <hi>Gorran</hi> vpon this place; for we may not doe to others, as we would be done vnto our ſelues, in one thing, or in ſome things, or in ſuch things as we liſt our ſelues: but in all iuſt, honeſt, lawfull and reaſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nable things whatſoeuer. And therefore <hi>Peter Lum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bard</hi> the Maſter of the Sentences, in <hi>lib.</hi> 3. <hi>diſtinct.</hi> 37. tels vs how theſe wordes are to bee taken and vnder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtood, <hi>de bonis quae inuicem exhibere debemus:</hi> And <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>retius</hi> vpon this place tels vs, how <hi>they are an vniuer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſall phraſe of ſpeaking, which</hi> (ſaith hee) <hi>muſt ſoberly hee vnderſtood;</hi> for we may not wantonly play with them, but refer them to that naturall Rule, <hi>To doe vnto others as we would be done vnto our ſelues.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>That men ſhould doe vnto you.]</hi> Not God, nor Angels, but men: becauſe many things may bee done vnto vs by them, which wee cannot doe to them againe. By <hi>Men</hi> is here meant the <hi>Sonnes of Men,</hi> as <hi>Iunius</hi> and <hi>Tre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>melius</hi> will haue it; or by <hi>men</hi> is here meant our <hi>neigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bours,</hi> as <hi>Dionyſius Carthuſianus</hi> vpon this place will haue it: for theſe words are a recapitulation of the commandements of the ſecond table which concernes our dutie towards our neighbour, and by our Neigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bour, towards all men. And this moſt plainly and po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſitiuely
<pb facs="tcp:25081:4" rendition="simple:additions"/>expreſſed by our Sauiour Chriſt in <hi>Math.</hi> 22. <hi>Chap.</hi> at the 37.39. and 40. <hi>verſes.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Euen ſo doe ye to them.]</hi> this word, <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, <hi>So,</hi> is redun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dant, ſaith <hi>Piſcator</hi> vpon this place. And yet (ſaith he) it notes the argument of Similies: for as we would haue comfort and counſell to be giuen vnto vs by others: ſo we muſt giue it to them againe. And as we would haue mercy, compaſſion and all other things expedient to be ſhewne vnto vs by others, ſo we muſt ſhew it to them likewiſe: becauſe naturall reaſon and inducement ought to bring vs to know that it is our dutie no leſſe to loue others then our ſelues: and to doe no worſe vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to them, then we would they ſhould do vnto vs. And therefore this Naturall reaſon and inducement hath drawne theſe ſeuerall Rules and Canons, for the bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter direction of our liues: <hi>Becauſe we would take no hurt, we therefore our ſelues muſt doe none. Sith we would not be extreamely dealt with all; we our ſelues muſt auoid all extremity in our dealing: we muſt vtterly abſtaine from all violence and wrong to others, ſeeing willing by we would haue none done to our ſelues.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>For this is the law and the Prophets,]</hi> that is, the do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine and meaning of the Morall Law of <hi>Moſes</hi> and the <hi>Prophets,</hi> do all teach and tend to this end to haue vs doe to others as we would bee done to our ſelues; for hereby our loue is ſhewen to others, which loue is all in all, the end and the fulfilling of the law, as the Apoſtle tels vs, <hi>Rom.</hi> 13.8. <hi>Owe nothing to any man but this, to loue one another: for he that loueth another, hath fulfilled the Law.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>For this is the Law.]</hi> The Law in generall is the ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry wiſedome of Nature, the rule of right and reaſon, and a directiue rule vnto goodneſſe of operation. And
<pb facs="tcp:25081:5" rendition="simple:additions"/>it is vſed for all kinde of doctrrine that doth preſcribe any thing. And therefore of the <hi>Hebrewes</hi> it is called <hi>Thorah,</hi> of <hi>Thor,</hi> which is <hi>ordinauit,</hi> or (as ſome will haue it) of <hi>Iadah,</hi> which is <hi>Docuit;</hi> becauſe it teacheth euery one his dutie both towards God and man. And in this ſenſe the Goſpell is called a Law as appeares by the Prophet <hi>Eſay</hi> in <hi>Chap.</hi> 2. <hi>verſe</hi> 3.</p>
            <p>But the Law in ſpeciall <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> by excellency doth ſhew all the old teſtament, as appeares by the Apoſtle <hi>Paul, Rom.</hi> 3.19. By Law here is meant, the moral Law of <hi>Moſes</hi> called <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> which is a perpetual rule of li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing wel; vnto which the maners of all people are to be directed, &amp; ſubiected both towards God and towards their Neighbour. And this is moſt briefly and plainly ſet down in the <hi>Decalogue</hi> or ten commandements; the matter or obiect of which is the loue of God and the loue of our neighbour, which loue of our neighbour is nothing els, but to <hi>doe, as we would be done vnto.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>And the Prophets.]</hi> There were Prophets in <hi>ſpeciall,</hi> and Prophets in <hi>generall.</hi> Prophets in <hi>ſpeciall,</hi> were they that did excell in wiſedome, by the ſingular gift of the holy Ghoſt, and did foretell things to come, either to the Church or to any of the faithfull. Such were <hi>Aga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bus,</hi> and the 4 daughters of <hi>Philip</hi> the Euangeliſt. Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phets in <hi>generall,</hi> were they that did excell in the ſingu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lar gift of interpreting the Scriptures. And ſuch are the learned <hi>Interpreters</hi> of the Scripture at this day, as ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peares by the Apoſtle <hi>Paul,</hi> 1. <hi>Cor.</hi> 14.29.32.</p>
            <p>There were <hi>Prieſts</hi> and <hi>Prophets,</hi> but there was a dif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ference betweene them. The <hi>Prieſts</hi> were alwaies out of the tribe of <hi>Leui,</hi> the <hi>Prophets</hi> out of other tribes. The <hi>Prieſts</hi> were not onely to pray and to teach, but to adminiſter holy things: the <hi>Prophets</hi> did not ſo.
<pb facs="tcp:25081:5" rendition="simple:additions"/>The <hi>Preiſts</hi> might erre as <hi>Aaron,</hi> but the <hi>Prophets,</hi> as farre forth as they were <hi>Prophets,</hi> and inſpired with the ſpirit of the Lord, could not erre. And therefore the ſpirit of Prophecie, was giuen to <hi>Eliſha,</hi> as it was to <hi>Elias</hi> 2. <hi>King.</hi> 2.15.</p>
            <p>True <hi>Prophets</hi> were called <hi>Seers,</hi> as in 1. <hi>Sa.</hi> 9.9. They were called <hi>Seers,</hi> becauſe they did Prophecie by viſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons or apparations obiect to the eye or the mind: or as <hi>S. Ierome</hi> tells vs in his <hi>Epiſtle</hi> to <hi>Paulinus, quia vide<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bant eum, quem <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>aeteri non vedebant.</hi> They did pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phecie either by dreames ſent from aboue, or by ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſe word, or by an inward inſpiration of the ſpirit of God, or by the apparition of an Angell repreſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting God, or by the mouth of God himſelfe familiar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly ſpeaking vnto them, as he ſpeake to <hi>Moſes,</hi> to whom he is ſaid to ſpeake mouth to mouth as in <hi>Numb</hi> 12.8. To this purpoſe the Apoſtle <hi>S. Paul</hi> ſpeaketh in <hi>Heb.</hi> 1.1. &amp; 2 where he ſaith; <hi>At ſundry times, and in di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uers manners, God in the old time, ſpake vnto our Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers by the Prophets; But is theſe laſt dayes he hath ſpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken vnto vs by his Sonne, whom hee hath made heyre of all things.</hi> By his Sonne he tels vs what the <hi>Law</hi> is: by his Sonne he tels vs what the <hi>Prophets</hi> are: by his Son hee tels vs, how the <hi>Law</hi> and the <hi>Prophets</hi> are nothing elſe, but to doe vnto others, as we would be done vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to our ſelues. <hi>Therefore whatſoeuer ye would that men ſhould doe to you, euen ſo doe yee to them, for this is the Law and the Prophets.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The point of Doctrine and obſeruation that ari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeth from hence may be this. <hi>To doe as wee would bee done vnto,</hi> is <hi>a generall rule of Iuſtice, and he ſumme of the Law and the Prophets.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Although this Point is ſo plaine and pregnant, that
<pb facs="tcp:25081:6" rendition="simple:additions"/>it need no farther diſcourſe, nor any more proofe to be aſſured of his goodneſſe, becauſe as ſoone as it is al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leadged, yet it is acknowledged to bee good; yet giue me leaue, I beſeech you to goe farther with it, and to ſhew vnto you the dignitie of it, with the Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thor and affirmation, the benefite of it with the <hi>effects,</hi> and the neceſſity of it, with the <hi>ſubiects, obiects,</hi> and the <hi>end.</hi> And to proue and approue all this by teſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monie of <hi>Scriptures,</hi> examples of <hi>Scriptures,</hi> teſtimony of ancient <hi>Fathers,</hi> and late <hi>writers, Emperours, Kings Philoſophers,</hi> and heathen people, led only by inſtinct of Nature.</p>
            <p>Great is the dignitie of this generall rule of <hi>Iuſtice,</hi> not only becauſe it is a Principle of Law and Nature, the root of Iuſtice, the foundation of equitie, and <hi>Lex inſcripta ſcripta,</hi> as S. <hi>Ambroſe</hi> tels vs in viſion 5. vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the 10. Chapter of the <hi>Reuel</hi> But becauſe it is a pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcript rule of our Sauiour Chriſt himſelfe. It was his own ſpeech an bleſſed counſell to his Diſciples. It was a breath of his mouth, who was not as a man that he ſhould lye, nor as the ſonne of man that he ſhould re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pent. And it was not by him barely ſpoken, but affir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>matiuely ſpoken; becauſe as the Law is of greater perfection, ſo that which is affirmatiue, is of grea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter perfection alſo, though affirmatiue precepts, as the Schoole-men tels vs, <hi>obligant ſemper, non pro ſemper, ſed tantum in loco &amp; tempore neceſſitatis.</hi> And it was by him not onely affirmatiuely ſpoken, but it was ſtrongly alſo inferred, concluded, and pithily vr<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged to his diſciples aboue any other thing.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Therefore whatſoeuer ye would that men ſhould doe to you, euen ſo doe yee to them, for this is the Law and the Prophets.</hi> The benefit of this generall rule of Iuſtice is
<pb facs="tcp:25081:6" rendition="simple:additions"/>great, and the effects good and goldly; for it will cauſe euery one of vs to liue honeſtly and vprightly in his place and calling, and neuer to binde any one of theſe three ſinnes together; which by many and too many are bound together in this age: <hi>Periury, falſe teſtimonie, iniury.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>This will make vs draw neere vnto Chriſts exam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, and to follow his ſteps. And this will ſtill pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duce in vs theſe <hi>effects,</hi> to loue God truly, our neigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bour vnfainedly, and to giue vnto euery one his due and his dutie, without any wrong or iniury.</p>
            <p>The <hi>effects</hi> of this generall rule of Iuſtice, cannot better be opened, then S. <hi>Auſten</hi> doth open them, in <hi>lib.</hi> 3. <hi>Cap.</hi> 14. <hi>de doct. Chrift,</hi> where he ſaith thus, <hi>Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cere alijs quod tibi vis fieri, ſententia eſt, &amp;c. To doe as thou wouldeft be done vnto, is a ſentence which all nations vnder heauen haue agreed vpon. Referre this ſentence</hi> (ſaith he) <hi>to the loue of God, and it extinguiſheth all hai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nous offences: referre this ſentence to the loue of thy neigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bour, and it baniſheth all grieuous wrongs out of the world.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The neceſſity of this generall rule of Iuſtice is great, in reſpect of the <hi>ſubiects,</hi> the <hi>obiects,</hi> and the <hi>end.</hi> The <hi>ſubiects,</hi> becauſe we are all Chriſtians and brethren, and haue one and the ſame God for our Creator, one and the ſame Chriſt for our Sauiour, and one and the ſame holy Ghoſt for our ſanctifier and preſeruer. The <hi>obiects,</hi> becauſe it reſpecteth right, and the good gouernmet of humane ſocieties: and the <hi>end,</hi> becauſe it was ordained by Chriſt himſelfe for the generall good one of another, teaching vs not only to be pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uatiue in ceaſing to doe ill, but ſtill to bee poſitiue in doing good one to another.</p>
            <p>Wee are not ſent into this world onely to ſpeake
<pb facs="tcp:25081:7" rendition="simple:additions"/>well, but to doe well, and to doe well and truly that which belongs to our ſeuerall places and callings. It is better to doe and ſay not, then to ſay, and doe not; ſpeculation is not ſo hard as practice. It is much more eaſie for any one to know then to do, to diſcourſe then to worke; and to beleeue as he ought, then to liue as he ſhould. And therefore our Sauiour Chriſt and his diſciples in all their ſpeeches, and in all their writings do ſpecially admoniſh vs to do well, &amp; do ſpeak much more of things to be done, then of things to be ſpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>k<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>n; and much more of vertuous liuing, then of right bele<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>uing: for, <hi>non verbaſed aduerbia corenantur.</hi> The Lord our God is ſaid to loue <hi>Aduerbs.</hi> He reſpects not how good, but how well thoſe things are which we doe; and our Sauiour Chriſt himſelfe began <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> to doe and to teach; firſt to doe, and then to teach, <hi>Act.</hi> 1. <hi>verſe</hi> 1.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Teſtimonies of Scriptures.</note>In <hi>Leuit.</hi> 19 <hi>verſe</hi> 11. we read how the Lord our God commanded <hi>Moſes</hi> to ſpeake vnto all the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gregation of Iſrael, and to ſay thus vnto them in a ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gatiue precept: <hi>Ye ſhall not ſteale, nor deale falſly, nor lie one to another;</hi> which is in effect, <hi>yee ſhall not doe to o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers, but as ye would be done vnto your ſelues.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>To bias</hi> gaue this generall rule of <hi>Iuſtice</hi> to his ſonne, but in a negatiue precept alſo, which bindeth at all times. <hi>My Sonne</hi> (ſaith he) <hi>that which thou wouldeſt not haue others to doe vnto thee, doe not to them at any time.</hi> Tob. chap. 4. <hi>verſe</hi> 15.</p>
            <p>Our Sauiour <hi>Chriſt</hi> not onely in <hi>Mat.</hi> 7 12. but al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo in <hi>Luke</hi> 6.31. gaue this generall rule of <hi>Iuſtice</hi> againe to his Diſciples, and to a great company of people that came from <hi>Iudea</hi> and <hi>Ieruſalem,</hi> and from the coaſts of <hi>Tyre</hi> and <hi>Sidon</hi> to heare him. <hi>And as ye would
<pb facs="tcp:25081:7" rendition="simple:additions"/>that men ſhould doe to you, ſo doe ye to them likewiſe.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The Apoſtle S. <hi>Paul</hi> gaue this generall rule of <hi>Iu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtice</hi> to <hi>Titus</hi> his naturall ſonne according to the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon faith, as appeares <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>is 2 <hi>Chap.</hi> to <hi>Titus</hi> 11. and 12. <hi>verſes,</hi> whe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>e he ſaith thus, <hi>The grace of God which bringeth ſaluation vnto all men, hath appeared, and tea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cheth vs, that we ſhould liue ſoberly righteouſly and god<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly in this preſent world.</hi> To liue righteouſly, what is it any other thing in effect, then to doe as we would be done vnto?</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Examples of Scriptures.</note>
               <hi>Obadiah,</hi> the gouernour of <hi>Ahabs</hi> houſe, remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bred and followed this generall rule of <hi>Iuſtice,</hi> to doe, as he would be done vnto, for when <hi>Iezabel</hi> deſtroyed the Prophets of the Lord, he tooke an hundred Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phets, and hid them by fifties in acaue, and fed them with bread and water. 1. <hi>King.</hi> 18. That good widow of <hi>Sarepta</hi> remembred and followed this generall rule of <hi>Iuſtice,</hi> to doe as ſhe would be done vnto; for ſhee tooke pitty and compaſſion vpon <hi>Elias,</hi> relieued him in his greateſt neceſſity, and ſuſtained him with part of that poore pittance that was left her, 1. <hi>King. ch.</hi> 17.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Samuel</hi> offered to God by his Mother, thrice called and made a Prophet, remembrad and followed this generall rule of <hi>Iuſtice,</hi> to doe as he would be done vnto; for, he boldly and ſtoutly ſtood vp vnto all Iſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rael and ſaid, <hi>Whoſe Oxe haue I taken? or, whoſe Aſſe haue I taken? or, whom haue I done wrong to? or, whom haue I hurt?</hi> That was not all; he left not there, but went father and ſaid, <hi>At whoſe hands haue I receiued any bribes to blind mine eyes therewith,</hi> 1, Sam. 12.3.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Simeon</hi> in <hi>Ieruſalem, Cornelius</hi> in <hi>Ceſarea,</hi> and <hi>Lidia</hi> the ſeller of purple in the City of the <hi>Thiatirians.</hi> And the very Barbarians, as in Act 28.2. remembred and
<pb facs="tcp:25081:8" rendition="simple:additions"/>followed this generall rule of Iuſtice, to doe as they would be done vnto; for they gently intreated <hi>Paul</hi> and his company when they came to ſhore in the Ile <hi>Melita,</hi> kindled a good fire and receiued euery one of them.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Teſtimonie of ancient Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers.</note>That mirror of vnderſtanding, and learned Father S. <hi>Auſtin</hi> in <hi>l.</hi> 1. <hi>cap. vlt. conf.</hi> in his <hi>ſer. ad frat. in eremo,</hi> in a tract which he writeth <hi>de decem chordis,</hi> ſpeaketh there of this generall rule of Iuſtice, and ſpecially in his 96. Sermon <hi>de tempore;</hi> where he ſaith thus; <hi>De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cem precepta ad duo illa referuntur vt diligamus Deum &amp; Proximum. Et duo illa ad vnum illud, quod vnum eſt; Quod tibi non vis, alteri ne feceris. Ibi decem, ibi duo continentur praecepta.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>That mellifluous Father <hi>S. Bernard</hi> in his 77. Epi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtle, and in a tract which he writes <hi>de triplici bonorum genere,</hi> cals to doe as we would be done vnto, <hi>natura<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lem legem ſocietatis cui concordat Euangelium, Haec eſt lex naturalis ſocietatis</hi> (ſaith he) <hi>vt omnia quaecunque nobis fieri velimus, alijs faciamus.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Peter Lumbard,</hi> the maſter of the Sentences, ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proues this ſame in <hi>lib.</hi> 3. <hi>diſtinct.</hi> 37. where ſpeaking of the commandements of the ſecond Table, cals to doe as we would be done vnto; <hi>naturalem legem, cui concordat Euangelium, &amp; lex moralis praeceptionis. Hoc veritas ſcripſit in corde hominis</hi> (ſaith <hi>Lumbard) &amp; quia non legebatur in corde, iterauit in tabulis, vt voce fo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rinſecus admota, rediret ad cor.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>S. Ambroſe</hi> viſion 4. in 8. chap. of the <hi>Reuel,</hi> ſpeak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing there of the holy men that liued before the floud, ſaith thus of them; <hi>Quamuis nullum legem niſi natu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ralem habuerunt, tamen hoc quibuſcunque poterant ſua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſſe conati ſunt, vt Deum creatorem ſuum timerent &amp;
<pb facs="tcp:25081:8" rendition="simple:additions"/>ligerent, &amp; quod quis pati non vellet, alteri non faceret.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Gregory the great,</hi> in <hi>lib.</hi> 10. <hi>Moral. in cap.</hi> 11. of <hi>Iob.</hi> in the beginning of the Chapter, tels vs there, That to doe as we would be done vnto, is comman<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded and commended both in the old and new Teſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, ſaith he, <hi>per iuſtum Tobiam,</hi> and in the new Te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtament, <hi>per veritatem ipſam,</hi> which is our Sauiour Chriſt. <hi>Quibus duobus</hi> (ſaith <hi>Gregorie</hi>) <hi>vtriuſque te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtamenti mandatis, per vnum malitia compeſcitur, per aliud benignitas prorogatur.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>To theſe may bee added <hi>Gratian</hi> in his <hi>golden De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crees,</hi> 1. <hi>part.</hi> 1. <hi>dictinct.</hi> the firſt words of all the booke which are theſe, <hi>Genus humanum duobus regitur, natu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rali videlicet iure &amp; moribus: naturale ius eſt, quod in in lege &amp; Euangelio continetur, quo quiſque iubetur a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lij facere, quod ſibi vult fieri, &amp; prohibetur alij inferre, quod ſibi nollet fieri,</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Teſtimony of late writers.</note>
               <hi>Zuinglius</hi> hath written at large vpon this, in 7. <hi>Chap. Mat. in pag.</hi> 28.29. And there hee tels vs, how our Sauiour Chriſt doth call it, <hi>fundamentum natura<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lis iuris,</hi> becauſe hee was the reformer of our nature corrupted by <hi>Adam.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Aretius</hi> vpon this place tels vs the like, how theſe words are a natural Law and the precepts of right are, as he there tels vs; <hi>honeſte viuere, alterum non laedere, ius ſuum cuique tribuere.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Beza, Bullinger, Caluin, Hemingius, Piſcator,</hi> with many others, all agree and concurre in this; that to doe as wee would be done vnto, is a generall rule of <hi>Iuſtice,</hi> a Sentence teaching all charitie, humanitie, moderation and good dealing one to another, and a <hi>ſentence</hi> (as it were) pointing out the way to eternall bliſſe and happineſſe.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:25081:9" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>
               <hi>Alexander Seuerus</hi> the Emperour, had this for his <hi>Symbole,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Emperours.</note> as <hi>Bullinger</hi> tells vs in <hi>Decade</hi> 11. <hi>Serm.</hi> 1. <hi>pag.</hi> 93. <hi>This</hi> (ſaith <hi>Bullinger</hi>) <hi>hee had often in his mouth: this he commanded to be engrauen and writen in his Pallace, and other of his buildings. Hoc coluit in la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rario ſuo</hi> (ſaith <hi>Bullinger.</hi>) and when any one of his diſorderly ſouldiers was to be puniſhed, hee would haue this ſpoken vnto him by the voyce of a Crier. <hi>Quod tibi hoc alteri.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Traian</hi> the Emperour, a great obſeruer of Iuſtice, and called the Darling of Mankinde, would very of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten ſay, how he himſelfe and all others<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> muſt doe as they would be done vnto; and how Subjects ought to be ſuch towards their Prince, as they would haue their Prince to be towards them.</p>
            <p>It is written in the life of <hi>Auguſtus</hi> the Emperour, how one <hi>Zonaras</hi> did often remember this generall rule of Iuſtice to <hi>Auguſtus</hi> the Emperour, and would ſay to him, <hi>Siipſe alijs feceris, quae tibi fieri velles, non peccabis quippiam, omnia ſuauiſſimè &amp; felicitèr admini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrabis, &amp; nullo cum periculo vitam deges.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>That learned Lawyer <hi>Vlpian,</hi> principall Counceller to <hi>Alexander Seuerus</hi> the Emperour, framed this as as a Conſtitution, which is found in the <hi>Pandects,</hi> that is, the volume of the Ciuill Law, called the <hi>Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geſts.</hi> And this was done by the commandement of <hi>Iuſtinian,</hi> that learned and worthy Emperour.</p>
            <p>That of our wiſe,<note place="margin">Kings.</note> worthy, learned, and of bleſſed and happy memory King <hi>Iames</hi> deceaſed, may ſerue for all the reſt in his <hi>Baſilicon doron, li.</hi> 2. <hi>pag.</hi> 6. where ſhewing to his Son Prince <hi>Henry</hi> what formes were to be vſed with other Princes, he ſaith thus vnto him, <hi>Vſe all other Princes as thy brethren, honeſtly and kindly.
<pb facs="tcp:25081:9" rendition="simple:additions"/>Striue with euery one of them in courteſie and in kindnes, and as with all men, ſo ſpecially with them be plaine and truthfull euer keeping that Chriſtian Rule, to doe as yee would be done vnto.</hi> Where we ſee King <hi>Iames</hi> cals it a Chriſtian rule, and would haue his Sonne Prince <hi>Henry</hi> euer to keepe it.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Philoſophers and Heathen people.</note>
               <hi>Pythagoras</hi> and <hi>Plato, Socrates</hi> and <hi>Xenophon</hi> with many others, taught this Philoſophy and generall rule of Iuſtice, to do as they would be done vnto, and very carefully obſerued it in their life and conuerſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion. So did <hi>Solon</hi> and <hi>Ariſtides</hi> among the Athenians, <hi>Ageſilaus</hi> and <hi>Lycurgus</hi> among the Lacedemonians, <hi>Curius Fabricius,</hi> and <hi>Numa Pompilius</hi> among the Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manes, <hi>Xamelzis</hi> among the Gothes, <hi>Zaleuchus</hi> a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong the Locrians, <hi>Triſmegiſtus</hi> among the Egyp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tians, and <hi>Dunwallo Mulmutius</hi> among the old Brit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tons of this Land. Nay more, and that which is ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry ſtrange. That diuiliſh Impoſtor, and damnable wretch <hi>Mahomet</hi> hath recommended this generall rule of Iuſtice, to doe as we would be done vnto, and hath inſerted it among the 8. Ordinances, which hee left to the Muſalmans, telling them how they were ſent downe from heauen by the Angell <hi>Gabriel.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>This alſo the heathen haue not obſcurely inſinua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, by making <hi>Themis,</hi> which is Law or right, a God<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deſſe<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> by building a Temple vnto her in <hi>Beoetia,</hi> and by making her to be the Daughter of Heauen and earth; for heauen and earth doe applaud this gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall rule of Iuſtice, to doe as we would be done vnto: it is <hi>the Royall Law of Loue;</hi> it was taught by our Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uiour Chriſt, deliuered by the law of Nature, and ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerued by Heathen people, led onely by inſtinct of Nature.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:25081:10" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>Seeing then that the dignitie of this generall rule of Iuſtice is ſo great with the Author and affirmation, the benefit of it is ſo great with the effects, and the ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſity of it is ſo great, with the <hi>ſubiects, obiects,</hi> and the <hi>end.</hi> And ſeeing this is proued and approued by teſtimonies of Scriptures, examples of Scriptures, te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtimonies of ancient Fathers and late Writers, Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perours, Kings, and Philoſophers, and Heathen peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple led by inſtinct of Nature. It is fit and worthy to be remembred and followed of vs, and to be written vpon the tables of our hearts with the point of a Dia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mond, that it may neuer be forgotten; for it is old Philoſophie and Chriſtian Religion; it is the end and the ſcope of all the Commandements of the ſecond Table, and the onely type and token of euery good Chriſtian. <hi>Therefore, whatſoeuer yee would that men ſhould doe to you, euen ſo doe ye to them; for this is the Law and the Prophets.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>That learned Father <hi>S. Auſtin</hi> in his 54. Epiſtle, tels vs there, that we may <hi>occupare negotioſiſſimum in Republica virum proemio;</hi> we may not hold a man of the greateſt employment in the Common-weale with a long preface. If not with a long Preface, then not with a long diſcourſe. Pardon therefore my bold<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe (right honourable and reuerend <hi>Iudges</hi>) if I firſt ſpeake to you, and tell you, that this generall rule of Iuſtice, to doe as ye would be done vnto, is fit and worthy to be remembred of you who are <hi>loquentes le<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges,</hi> chiefe guardians of iuſtice, and Altars vnto which ſuch flye for ſuccour and reliefe, as are wronged and iniuried. By this you ſhall take <hi>Gallioes</hi> courſe, as it is in <hi>Act.</hi> 18.16. to driue away friuolous and iniuri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous ſuites from the iudgement ſeat. By this you ſhall
<pb facs="tcp:25081:10" rendition="simple:additions"/>be faithfull Stewards of the higheſt <hi>Iudge;</hi> and by this you ſhall keepe ſafe and ſound thoſe two Salts that are in you, the Salt of knowledge, and the Salt of Conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence; which Salt of Conſcience is the inward Court wherein the higheſt <hi>Iudge</hi> of all doth ſit.</p>
            <p>This generall rule of Iuſtice is fit to be remembred and followed of you alſo, who are Magiſtrates, and in the Commiſſion of peace, the Princes eyes to ſee withall, and the Princes hands to worke withall, the <hi>Ephori</hi> of the Common-weale, and the Ouer-ſeers of common quietneſſe. This will make you good and iuſt, like <hi>Ioſoph</hi> of <hi>Arimathea.</hi> This will make <hi>Iuſtice</hi> in you neuer to draw her breath faintly, or to be per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerted with any feare or fauour, paſſion or precipita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, malice or preſumption; and this will make you like <hi>Atropos</hi> to cut off the web of many debates and quarrels at home among your neighbours, and to be of that worthy Lord Iudge <hi>Dyers</hi> minde, who when there came before him any controuerſies of poore men to be tryed at the Aſſiſes, would vually ſay, that <hi>either the parties themſelues were wilfull, or their neigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bours at home vncharitable, becauſe their ſuites were not quietly ended at home.</hi> Many poore mens ſuits may be quietly ended at home by you, who are the Iudges eyes. It is well knowne that ſome of you doe ſo. O that all would doe ſo. It is a bleſſed action to doe ſo; for, <hi>Bleſſed are the peace-makers.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>This generall rule of Iuſtice is fit alſo to be remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bred and followed of you who practiſe and profeſſe the Lawes, and plead preſent matters for your <hi>Clients;</hi> for this will make you ſquare, ſound, and ſincere in all your actions, and to auoid all thoſe foule aſperſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons and ſcandals that are caſt vpon you of bribery,
<pb facs="tcp:25081:11" rendition="simple:additions"/>corruption, and extortion, of ſpinning out ſuits to the downfall of the <hi>Clients</hi> eſtates of wrangling and wreſtling as the <hi>Greeke Sophiſters</hi> were wont to doe, to make the worſe the better: and that which is worſt inded, of animating and ſetting of ſome malicious make-bates to ſow <hi>Cadmus</hi> teeth abroad, and like <hi>Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lamanders</hi> ſtill to liue in the fire of debate and diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cord among their neighbours.</p>
            <p>The Law is of maſculine force, as Saint <hi>Auſtin</hi> tels vs vpon the 59. Pſalme; for though in the Latine tongue it is of the <hi>feminine gender,</hi> yet in the Greeke tongue it is of the <hi>maſculine gender,</hi> becauſe it is of more maſculine force and power, <hi>Regit, &amp; non regi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tur.</hi> It rules, and it doth not rule with any reſpect of perſons, or with any floting, or imaginary affection: for if it hath but one ſoule, which is reaſon; and one onely function which is the peace and quietneſſe of States and Common-weales: which peace and qui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>etneſſe of States and Common-weales, ſhall the better be eſtabliſhed and continued, if you follow this gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall rule of Iuſtice, to doe as you would be done vnto.</p>
            <p>This Chriſtian and generall rule of Iuſtice is fit to be remembred ad followed of you who are Actors and commence ſuites; of you that are witneſſes to te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtifie and giue in <hi>euidence;</hi> of you that are <hi>Iuries,</hi> and bring in <hi>verdicts;</hi> and of you that bee <hi>Conſtables,</hi> and exhibite <hi>Bils.</hi> O this will make you neuer to open the ſluces of any fauour, feare or partiality to any, neuer to ſtraine out gnats, and to ſwallow downe Camels, and neuer to be ſo raſh with your mouthes as to ſay, <hi>Sibboleth,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Iudg. 12.6.</note> for <hi>Shiboleth,</hi> great for little, or little for great, cold for hot, or hot for cold, man-ſlaughter for wilfull murther, or wilfull murther for man-ſlaughter.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:25081:11" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>This Chriſtian and generall rule of Iuſtice, is fit to be remembred and followed of all you that bee here preſent, of what age or condition, ranke or faſhion ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>euer ye bee; for by this you ſhall neuer be barbarous nor cruel one to another; you ſhall neuer ſtatue nor ſtrip one another, and neuer ſeeke the downefall and confuſion one of another by any vniuſt meanes, or iniurious courſes.</p>
            <p>We are all by nature louers of our ſelues, and wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lingly we would haue no harme nor hurt done to our ſelues; the like we muſt do vnto others; we may not harme nor hurt them in their bodies, goods or name; for what ſaith <hi>Salomon</hi> in <hi>Pro.</hi> 3.29. <hi>Intend none hurt to thy neighbour, ſeing he doth dwell without feare by thee.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The loue of our neighbour is no meane matter, It is not meanly graced by our Sauiour Chriſt himſelfe; for there are but ten commandements, and no leſſe them ſixe of them concernes our neighbour. Theſe 10. are contracted into two; one of them is our neigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bours. The firſt is great; the ſecond is like vnto it, which is our neighbours; the Law and the Prophets depend vpon the one, and the Law and the Prophets depend vpon the other. This is plainly proued by the Apoſtle, <hi>Gal.</hi> 5.14. <hi>All the Law is fulfulfilled in one word, which is this, Thou ſhalt loue thy neighbour as thy ſelfe.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The <hi>Mathematicians</hi> tell vs, that of all figures, a a <hi>Circle</hi> is the moſt abſolute, becauſe the beginning and the end concurres in one. Such is this generall rule of Iuſtice. It comes from Chriſt in grace, and ends in Chriſt by the workes of grace. The then that neglect this generall rule of Iuſtice, and doe not as they would be done vnto, haue little or no grace in them; they can hope to heare well of none but of
<pb facs="tcp:25081:12" rendition="simple:additions"/>cowards and flatterers; and they can neuer haue a good Conſcience in them, which is a continuall feaſt, and the beſt friend that is in the world. <hi>Plerique fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man, pauci conſcientiam verentur,</hi> ſaith <hi>Seneca,</hi> they little reſpect that, they can play faſt and looſe with that at their pleaſure, &amp; they can make it of what ſize or faſhion they liſt themſelues. They can vſe it as <hi>Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cruſtes</hi> the Gyant did thoſe whom hee layd in his bed; when they were too long, he had an axe to cut them ſhorter; and when they were too ſhort, hee had a racke to ſtretch them longer. <hi>Conſcientia eſt cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dis ſcientia,</hi> and Gods golden dowry beſtowed vpon the ſoule: and yet it hath had them worſt hap, that any word had in the world, in the Common weale, &amp; eſpecially in the Church of Chriſt; for neuer as yet could it be found in her full ſillables at once, but ſome ſillable or other was wanting in her. <hi>Faſciculus tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>porum</hi> tels vs this, in <hi>A.D.</hi> 1426.</p>
            <p>In the Apoſtles time (ſaith hee) there was <hi>con</hi> and <hi>ſci,</hi> but <hi>entia</hi> was wanting; they had the endowment of the ſpirit, but not the endowment of poſſeſſions. Afterwards there was <hi>con</hi> and <hi>entia,</hi> but <hi>ſci</hi> was wan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting, they were not the learnedſt men. But in my time (ſaith he) <hi>con</hi> and <hi>ſci</hi> are both gone, and there is nothing left but <hi>entia,</hi> they haue all the Honours, Mannours, and fat of the Land. But we may now ſay that it is come round about againe, and it is with vs as it was at the firſt; we haue <hi>con</hi> and <hi>ſci,</hi> but our <hi>entia</hi> are called in queſtion by many embeziled, and by too many enuied and thought too much.</p>
            <q>
               <l>O nauis referunt in the noui fluctus.</l>
               <l>O quid agis? fortitèr occupaportum.</l>
            </q>
            <p>Wee may now well entertaine and renew that alle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>goricall
<pb facs="tcp:25081:12" rendition="simple:additions"/>ſpeech of the <hi>Lyricke</hi> Poet; <hi>O ſhip, new waues come and daſh vpon thee! O what doeſt thou? manfully and ſtrongly hold and keepe thine harbour and thy hauen.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Certainly, people are neuer miſerable till <hi>conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence</hi> turnes their enemy, then they are miſerable in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed; for, <hi>Nocte dieque ſuum geſtabunt pectore teſtem, Cui non ſanus erit.</hi> They ſhall carry about their wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe night and day; which witneſſe dyeth not.</p>
            <p>We ſhall all die, but our <hi>Conſcience</hi> ſhall not die; we may loſe our ſelues, but we cannot loſe our <hi>Conſcience;</hi> the light of it may be ſhadowed for a time, but it can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not be cleane put out. It ſhall appeare with vs at the day of iudgement, and then it ſhall ſpeake with vs or againſt vs. If againſt vs, then moſt miſerable wret<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches ſhall wee be; for then it ſhall be ſaid vnto vs; <hi>De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>part ye curſed into euerlaſting fire.</hi> But if it ſhall be with vs; then bleſſed and and happy ſhall we be; for then it ſhall be ſaid vnto vs, <hi>Come, ye bleſſed <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>f my Father, in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berite the Kingdome of heauen prepared for you from the beginning of the world.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>I feare the time is paſt, and willingly <hi>I</hi> would not be tedious vnto you. I will therefore conclude, and com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mit you and commend you to the Author of this ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerall rule of <hi>Iuſtice, Chriſt Ieſus</hi> our Sauiour: begging and beſeeching him to bleſſe, ſanctifie, guide and di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rect you all that you may ſtill remember and follow this generall rule of <hi>Iuſtice,</hi> to doe as ye would be done vnto in all your actions, and in all your life &amp; conuer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſation; that ſo you may liue in the feare, die in the fauour, reſt in the peace, riſe in the power, and at laſt remaine with him in euerlaſting glory, to whom with the Father, &amp;c.</p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
            <pb facs="tcp:25081:13"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:25081:13"/>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
